all right welcome to the idea cafe I'm
going to do a four part series over the
next four weeks seeing how the four
questions play up when we do them at
idea cafe so today's question is Who am
I
the other three questions are who are my
people what is my purpose and what do I
need so today is Who am I who would like
to start yeah I will because I'm really
excited about this notion I I really
like it a lot I think it's a really
simple and powerful engine to have at
the core of any kind of personal
development program right whatever that
might be
you know from education right through to
psychology right through to trauma
really no trauma healing all of that
kind of stuff I think I think that's a
really valuable cycle to have at the
center and so yeah like the two parts of
creating a vigorous healthy culture are
good people and good ways of going about
doing things right I think that that
solves the Google not solves it but I
mean if it's engaged in faithfully has
the potential to be the thing which is
forever creating better and better
people in the society so yeah I they're
in in question two there is one thing
which slightly troubles me but we'll get
to that when we talk about question two
but but the cycle as a whole beginning
with who am i and then in the context of
an ever increasing and deepening
knowledge of Who I am
how do I want to go about finding people
with whom I can collaborate you know
figuring out what what what is the what
is the what is the best contribution I
can make to the world and what do I need
to go about doing that I think it's
great I think it's great really simple
lovely thing
some things there do you want to answer
the question Who am I well like I said
this is a this is a constant work in
progress right so yeah okay so in my
current state of development if you like
I guess my answer to that question would
be something along the lines of I am
a portion of the universe which
temporarily has a boundary drawn around
it such that the illusion of separation
is lived out and so yes um something
like that something like that that's
that that's that's who am i right now
something along those lines
thanks David do you want to share do you
want me to share yeah so similar to Erik
think that there's something it's a
fractal question for me so I noticed
that I have my roles that I engaged in
and I've separated out from the working
class temporarily in order to figure out
more deeply what this question means but
I'm noticing that the the holographic
relationship between Who I am in my in
my family life to Who I am in my
neighborhood who I am in my and my
culture is changing I feel like I am a
convener of voices around a central
question of what is this changing moment
for us there is a something that I've
been feeling for a while that's coming
through in this I'll say only somewhat
with a wink I think that I have I'm a I
am somewhat of a wizard and collective
intelligence
so I mean wizard and kind of a Harry
Potter first year kind of I think I've
got some super powers for discerning
what's happening here and I have no idea
what I'm actually capable of but I'm
gonna have a sense of what what domains
to travel in which contexts to listen
more deeply to and where those
conversations are bearing fruit so
that's kind of the big overview of Who I
am I am a citizen of the world more than
have any particular nationality more so
which is an interesting notion and
trying to figure out how that how that
works and I'm I'm it
I am maturing in the liminal space like
yeah actually actually that's that feels
more accurate than the world
it's a citizen of the liminal space I'll
pause there thank you Who am I what a
question what a question I am a lot of
things I am a lot of like categories
that I pick and choose whether actually
pick and choose like it's my choice or
whether it's just part of who I am what
that of what part of that label applies
to me and what doesn't so I go through
like all of those labels I am a middle
child I grew up in Alberta and that
definitely has a imprint on my on my
soul but I more resonate with where I
live now on the coast in Vancouver it's
my home
I am a logical intellectual pursued
intelligence and knowledge I am someone
who's been through a lot of brain
changes I am someone who starred Ivor
sigh have both autism and a DD plus some
some very minor brain damage that has
had a huge impact on my life I am so I'm
all of my medical conditions and yet
none of them it's the interconnection of
all of them I have chronic fatigue and
fibromyalgia I've had my brain tumors I
am someone who is constantly figuring
out who I am including these big labels
that I don't know until I know them like
I didn't know I was queer until I was 36
I didn't know I was autistic till I was
39 and looking back on everything that
that repaints life as and knowing that
not only was am i queer and autistic I
wasn't supposed to know until I was 36
or 39 because I would have been
completely different if I had known I
was queer when I was 18 19 or by known I
was autistic my whole life its I am
someone who's just learning that I'm
never gonna know who I am it is gonna be
in constant unfolding and I am with
those two big epiphanies like what else
is coming down the line what else am i
that I don't know what
I am until I know it and what am I here
to give and I know that part of what is
here for me to do is conversations how
do we have a generative conversation how
do we have people show up be themselves
in a conversation and have magic and
beauty come out of that for ourselves
and for the world
and that's where my ideas keep generated
in that realm so I know that that's what
I'm here to do because I'm not what I
felt like I was here to be was create a
world that works for everyone it's
technology cooperative and I'm still
doing that but that's not as easy and as
mine as being part of a conversation and
that is that is Who I am I just want to
mention Remzi I know you're here in
listin if you want to pop in and chat
you don't have to share for the five
minutes just turn your camera on and
wave and then I'll add you but also
you're free to just sit there and listen
all right old David newark here so just
let me know but I won't be able to see
that you want to go on and let's see
turn on your camera and wave so all
right now we can open open up the
conversation either to do anything if I
add to my articles I feel having
listened to your two answers to who I am
that mine was just a little bit too meta
and and perhaps I should get down into
you know yeah that as you two have done
sort of what I don't know I guess what
the driving forces are I think in my
life right now yeah something something
like that and so yeah I really like that
actually there's elements of what both
of you said that I really like and
really identify David the citizen of the
world
there's a quote by Thomas Paine with
which you are no doubt familiar yeah I'm
a citizen of the world and my religion
is to do good I I like that I like the
simplicity of that and and I identify
with that I also very much identify what
Jubilee said in that you know it's a
journey it's not a destination who you
are it's a journey who you are is
forever changing and your knowledge of
who you are is forever changing and
deepening as well right and so it's a
it's somewhere where you never really
get right it's a it's a it's an
unfolding and uncovering and a pulling
back of Bale's and so I guess
what I would say my main thing is in
these times is connecting things
together and by that I mean both people
and ideas from different domains and and
and fusing them into my own thing I
guess that's an end and trying to I feel
I have a certain attitude for understand
I mean I'm not smart enough to come up
with them but I can understand other
people's big ideas and then distill the
essence out of them so that they are
more easily communicated to others I
feel that my role is something something
in that domain right though the
connecting of different groups of
basically like-minded people together
and translating all of those ideas into
a common language that they can all
understand something like that something
like that thank you I like the there's
something you just said and then I wrote
down Who am I
which is not a note that's not a note
that's not that's the conversation but
I'm sure it'll come back it does seem
that that this question is more involved
and alive than it's ever been before and
I love what you said Jubilee about the
fact that you don't even know what you
fully are right now right and so having
having conversation with Eric yesterday
actually we were talking about binary
and non binary right and so it's a just
take a look at binary and non binary
labels and even the labels do a poor job
of actually describing Who I am
I heard Nora Bateson say recently but
who I am is a description of like my
body is the description of Who I am and
it's such a different notion of the word
description right it's a description not
as a propositional or verbal list of
attributes in activities
as a living breathing embodied response
to my environment and my internal
response to that environment so it's a
it's a it is a very much like learning
to internalize my own authorship of my
participation in this larger context
which I'm also a part right i if I look
at it it trying to divide and I think
Daniels muckenberger does some really
good job of looking at this as well how
do I actually distinguish where I start
and I end right I can't exist without my
environment so I can't exist without my
body so there's a there's somewhat an
arbitrary line there it makes sense
because there's some interior feeling of
this but if I if I stick too tightly to
that distinction then I can pollute or
under undermine my environment such the
way this is the same as I can't with my
body right if I don't actually treat my
body like it's a the vehicle that I need
to respect in order to carry me to the
finish line
it's expendable I can just do whatever I
want to with it then it's not gonna
carry me very far all right so that
moment in time that I consider how wide
a window I look at magical augment to
Who I am
like who I think I am hmm try remember
of what I was going to write it was
actually when Eric was talking was there
was something coming up on if it can be
put into a job description it's not who
you are but like although you might be
an engineer you might be a doctor you
might be like someone had posted on one
of my and it's something I constantly
come up with in my own ego of like what
is my role in the tech cooperative when
I'm not a tech person right and it is I
don't know I have the vision I don't
know this is what's happening through me
and in me so it's not something I can
give a job description to and that is
normal when you're starting a business
like Elon Musk is the CEO of
of Tesla but what does he actually do
he's you know I mean he's Elon Musk's is
different than hiring someone who is a
CEO and there's something there of like
every human being is them right like my
job is to be Jubilee you can't put that
in a job description even if there's
many job descriptions I could maybe do
and so there was something there that
was like ya know I think it's an
important I think it's important notion
I think it goes even deeper than that
though it's not it's not even just about
job description it's it's it's about
your personal narrative if that becomes
too fixed too entrenched then it stifles
your ability to evolve and change right
and so the getting married to the idea
of who you are is is is it's a really
dangerous thing right well dangerous is
maybe the wrong word but it's a it's a
it's a regressive thing right it's a so
yeah the it's almost a question it
doesn't want an answer right as soon as
you come to an answer which you're happy
with and feels in some way final and
definitive then you stop traveling right
you've come to a halt which is like if I
label myself something even including a
profession right I'm an engineer then
I'm gonna have a connotation of what
that is and I might be leaving living
into it okay I can't do that because
engineers don't do that or I could not
be and just be like well that's okay I'm
an engineer and I still do this and so
yeah it's a very nebulous thing feels
feels worth bringing in here I think is
it Daniel who talks about this you know
there's being becoming this this this
you know you are you are what you are
but you are also constantly in a state
of becoming something else right and and
so yeah Who I am is also Who I am
becoming in the direction I am heading
in right is also part of who I am mm-hm
it's funny I suddenly think I am a
mythical creature who sometimes pretends
to be a cog in a machine in order to
pay the bills there is like this this
portion of society where we're all kind
of stuck at home and this is my normal
this is ninety percent of my normal
there was still ten percent that I've
reduced for sure I don't go to cohousing
right now but there's a openness that
happens when you're stuck in your own
house and I'm seeing it happen in on
social media people are like can we just
agree to like never go back to wearing
bras like why am I even putting on
makeup and I'm like both you can right
you can get dressed up to the night I
can tell you the number of times my kid
comes out her ballet outfit or a full
dress I'm like you know we're just a
knit but that's what she wants to do
what she wants to look like whereas me
I'm like pajamas all day every day giant
onesie anything I'm comfortable in
because it's my space and I and I think
that we start to give ourselves
permission or when we are around
ourselves as the number one person more
often that it's it's not the bras or
makeup or dressing up as bad or good
it's is it you what do you do when
you're by yourself how do you want to
appear like is there a reason to get
dressed up or is there not to be by
yourself well it really is kind of
interesting too because the the sense of
it you familiar with the notion of a
non-newtonian fluid you know like a wet
sand or the starch compound like when
it's under stress it's it acts like a
solid but when it's relaxed it acts like
a liquid and there's something like that
the more that I act like the more that I
perceive myself and act like I'm a cog
in the machine the more they feel like I
have a rigidity that actually functions
as a cog in the machine it's like okay
yeah my parts interleaved with the parts
of a social structure in a way that it
actually allows the social structure
some external influence to move through
me in a way that I can then benefit but
as soon as that pressure stops it's like
the the it's like it's I say it's kind
of like a slime mold right under the
right conditions it's doing something
it's striving it looks like it it looks
like an amoeba
and then when those conditions fail and
moisture level falls it turns into dust
and it's like oh that's interesting Who
am I when I don't have the confining
competing pressurized container that
holds that help yeah yeah yeah just as
you talk about because there's something
about a cog right which is very
impersonal and does the set all it does
is go round and round and round and
round and round right and it does what
it does entirely because the cogs next
we're also going round and round and
driving it in it's driving the next one
and it's very mechanical and very boring
and very soul-destroying kind of feeling
that that image as to it right I'm
wondering what an equivalent imagery
would be for because in a sense I mean
however evolved and beautiful the
Society is we are in a sense still cogs
in a machine right we are completely
dependent on those around us and they to
some extent depend on what we do right
we're that the connection between what
we think is not lost but it's not a hog
type thing there is there's a different
nature to it I'm wondering what imagery
would fit that kind of
interconnectedness that isn't so
restrictive mm-hmm and I think that I
don't know what your wording was David
but like the corn started to say non
Newtonian physics and because yeah the
COG when you were talking about I'm like
and you can't not be a cog right if you
are like I'm not gonna have this spoke
anymore I'm gonna be bigger I'm gonna be
smaller you don't fit into the Machine
and the Machine can't run and everything
breaks down we can't be individual cogs
right we can't reinvent ourselves as a
cog and remain a cog at the same time
there's something about the cornstarch
something about that like the pressure
makes that you can say you know what how
to try to be this calm today I'm gonna
try and like do this one but I might not
I might not hold that shape under and
then we'll see how it runs and we'll see
who can who can fit into this to this
this pressure applied when when
something is required of it its
structures itself right it creates a it
creates a rigid structure in response to
that and then when it when that is no
longer required
it becomes right and those things are no
longer fixed in position they're free to
move around again but then the next time
the system is under stress they are
required to once again line up and get
into position and and and and and be a
cog again so there's fluidity between
being cog and being non cog I mean I
don't know I mean that Jim rut made an
interesting point recently I think was
on rebel wisdom where he said that you
know being able to go into war mode is
part of the mess of stability of a
society right you know you don't wanna
be in that mode all the time you need to
have the ability to go into that mode
when circumstances dictate that that's
the appropriate response right and so
yeah that's that that fluid seems to do
that kind of there's that like the war
part of it the you need to be a cog in
the machine during this time period and
we have different connotations with
different jobs and different like the
people are right now doing so much free
labor for one another out of the
goodness of their heart is amazing yet
there's some free labor we're absolutely
not willing to do even though there's
nothing wrong like to go in and picking
vegetables from the field
go in and actually doing the the work
that needs to get done so we can be fed
mounts down the line is like a waiter
I'm not volunteering and doing that and
I'm you can't pay me enough to do it
like it's like both instead of like
listen there's food we need to eat we
have to find a way that this feels good
to do it that it is tapping into our
cognizant on making you it's like yeah
let's go over to the fields that's how
music let's pick the stuff right let's
not let's recruit we need this food
either system not rotting in the fields
how do we get it out with with within
our human capacity of wait that doesn't
feel good I don't want to go work for a
multinational corporation and not get
paid for it what's in it for me and
finding that what's in it for me those
did it for you and
I I want to I want to bring it back to
Jim ruts notion of you need to have a
war mode and to be able to go into that
you don't want to stay there but you
need to have that as an option and I
want to notice there's something you
know I haven't yet watched the rebel
wisdom dialogue with Nora Bateson and in
gym rat and a blue there's somebody else
in that conversation as well right right
okay so I haven't seen that but but Jim
often strikes me as very much
southern good old boy energy right and
it has that kind of that war war mindset
makes sense in a certain context and in
Nora Bateson is really interesting
because she's she looks much more at a
fluid kind of context so there's
something about the coronavirus and
covered 19 that is a very interesting
metaphor for looking at this if I see
myself as a cell and a multicellular
global organism then Who am I at war
with and just as the body's my body's
response if I catch the virus and my
body starts to react to it
it's at war but it can't quite there it
can't quite tell what is friend and what
is foe there's a lot of friendly fire
and unintentional casualties because the
the hyper attack mode the war machinery
is confused about how best to treat this
you know it may actually kill the
organism and perhaps that's actually
essential or the global organism so it's
an interesting notion of okay how do i
this is this is completely challenging
these notions of identity in a deep way
that that can be and
probably challenge it's challenging is
the wrong word it's it's very
destabilizing and yet there's something
I can find a way to to the tension of
what's being asked of me and what I'm
needing from the system so it's a it's a
it's a moment that liminal space really
describes it well I don't I I don't know
which ways up anymore right you know I'm
not I'm not sure war mode as maybe the
best term I mean that's the word that he
used right which is why I wish is why I
used it just just in repetition but hey
I don't think he actually means war in
that sense in that you're fighting
against an enemy rather it's in the way
that a nation does in times of war
everybody forgets their differences and
get on the same team to deal with this
thing right it's it's that so it's there
isn't necessarily an enemy it's it's the
the ability to all come together you
know to do one really important thing
right now that's that it's more about
that so maybe what I mean I yeah maybe
Wars just not a great word to using that
spots it brings whole bunch of stuff
with it right well it it also reminds
back you know back in the 60s 70s
cartoon strip Pogo we have met the enemy
he is us Fred yeah but that that notion
then is more true now than it's ever
been because there's a sense that if I'm
in war mode you know even that we have
to all align for a common purpose who's
defining the purpose where is the
narrative coming from do we yes do we
sell that to to trump and and the the
leaders of the world do we assign it to
the corporate leaders do we excite it to
the citizens who and you can see there
isn't isn't a narrative the one of the
conversations that Eric Weinstein has
recently says it looks like coronavirus
is real and there are casualties and
hospitals are empty how can both of
these be true at the same time it
looks likely our I don't know how to
make sense of that don't know how that
it saying that's all the hoax
everything's fine just go about your
business it's probably fatal saying it's
completely real everybody stay locked up
note and never go outside your house
this is the new normal and woods have to
learn to live with it is probably also
fatal this is an interesting time to be
a bore whatever whatever use that word
to be because for the first time in
human history we are in global society
and this war isn't against another human
right it isn't against another group of
humans that we can do human eyes it's
again something that's already to human
eyes and we have no way to argue with it
do you want to be like we can't even win
against it all we can do is kind of
figure it out from our from our side but
we're still at war with each other we're
still you know like you're you're an
over estimator and you you're gonna
destroy the economy because you're all
just letting our fascist governments
take over to the like no this is what
this is the best we can do right now for
our society it's the best we got going
on to know what to do and there's a real
cost that comes from everything we've
we've sewed that we're now reaping our
distrust in our media and governments
and our authoritative even if they are
democratic governments or it's like they
decide things and we follow or we don't
only eroded that trust and we don't
follow them anymore and nor should we
except for right now like this is really
weird flipping of like the enemy becomes
people who don't stand on your side
people who are not social distancing in
my case or from them people who are
social distancing right like how dare
you stay in your house you're the
problem like you don't understand you're
gonna destroy the economy I'm like well
the economy was destroying itself anyway
so this is just a faster kindergarten
apocalypse like something that we can
test out but the virus itself isn't like
the virus we can't argue with it it's
whatever it is whatever it's biology is
is what we're gonna have to figure out
and deal with
as a society and as as human beings and
there's nothing we can do about that we
can't change it it is interesting there
was a video taken in the UK
not long ago which went which meant sort
of semi viral of the same thing that
David was just mentioning someone going
around a hospital and going through Ward
after Ward after ward and just taking
film of empty beds and this guy arrested
he was he was put in jail apparently
didn't know anything about as far as I
can tell but was apparently put in jail
and so yeah it is it is odd isn't it
that there are all of these empty beds
and yet this narrative of we don't want
to overwhelm the Health Service it
doesn't look like it's anywhere near
overwhelm you know what I mean and and
and again just like that I'm not saying
what's right what's wrong but it is see
it is seemingly impossible to make sense
of that paradox right so just that just
to be clear you know and I saw someone
who gave a really good description of a
possible explanation for why there are
empty hospital beds one so just this
isn't to say this is the truth but this
is just a good counter narrative that to
be added in right
just because you CT hospital beds does
that mean that there's no virus well no
remember right now the numbers are still
the number of deaths or what and a
hundred and fifty thousand range
globally something like that whereas
last week it was 70,000 so if the
numbers can be believed we're doubling
and a week the number of deaths that's
given three weeks of isolation so far
right so and if I look at the chart if
it can be believed it's still heading up
but it's still a hundred thousand deaths
150,000 deaths globally it's still not
that much it's heading in the direction
and an exponential growth that that will
become a problem at some point and given
that it makes sense that hospitals are
saying let's not put any kind of
elective surgeries anything that can be
cleaned off the slates works we're
making sure that we have the hospital is
as empty as possible to prepare for this
coming onslaught it kind of like so if I
think of it in the way of sitting on the
beach in Indonesia during that during
the tidal wave hey well there's
something happen out there but the beach
is fine I'm cool
what's the problem well the problem is
that thing is heading this way and
getting bigger by the moment and just
standing here because the beach is fine
is a really bad idea
but it's difficult to the context wait a
minute how big is that how fast is it
moving what does that mean when it's
actually here at my doorstep when do I
need to actually say this is something I
need to deal with rather than oh that's
something I can ignore right I think
there's some validity in that but at the
same time they've also been plenty of
reports and plenty of videos of how
overwhelmed people are in the healthcare
system right you know doing 18-hour
shifts you know not in sufficient
protective equipment and everyone's
rushed off their feet and we haven't got
enough beds to put people and the IC
user overflowing we've got people in
corridors and bla bla bla bla bla right
so how does that fit in you know what I
mean I think it is it's it's like if we
think about it as war or think about it
you that analogy when one nation is at
war with another or like America is with
everyone over like with Iraq and
Afghanistan you have different bases
just cuz one base is overwhelmed and in
a fight doesn't mean every base at the
same time is and it doesn't mean those
bases are gonna up and leave either
they're there in case there's an
outbreak right there of war of fighting
and if things escalate they have their
people on the ground and that is what we
were treating this like a war we've
we've we've um people are on the ready
they're on the ready for this this tidal
wave of patients that may or may not
come because we it's based on math and
it's it's a two-week cycle it's like
well the people that are incubating it
right now are possibly the ones you're
gonna be on the respirators in two weeks
and then when they're on the respirators
in two weeks and they
passed it on to everybody else's them
the people in the respirators in another
two weeks now there's room for them
because if this exponential growth this
is the problem with with any central
authority our government is taking
action is like you know there were
critiquing Trump understandably because
he didn't shut it down soon enough but
if you had shut it down in January we're
already critical of our governments who
shut it down too early right like wait
our hospitals are empty and then when
because hospitals aren't people like
well then we need to leave our houses no
bridge alone this is like this is the
calm before the storm or it's not and
the calm remains and we did our job or
there's a storm and we need to stay here
well that's happening but the health
care workers that are overwhelmed in the
hospitals that are overwhelmed there's
ways to deal with that and move
personnel around and move and and get
those things ready but it always just
seems to me there's a disservice in and
I get why we do it but in stopping
information and putting that guy in jail
because he took because that information
being out there means everyone's like
how why are we in our houses we're gonna
leave and you don't want people to do
that but but then when you put him in
jail everyone's like wait they're lying
to us they're not letting us know the
truth and the truth is this is a dick
this is a disease we don't understand we
don't understand the implications of it
and we're learning and we're figuring it
out we're trying to get capacity to deal
with all the patients before they arrive
and our hospitals are empty like but
like some are overwhelmed and some
aren't and say like this is the truth
both of those things are truth but we
know it's a pretty small country if
you've got some hospitals are
overwhelmed and others are not then you
should be easily able to spread the
loads a little bit more I mean I agree I
get that that's not the case everywhere
right but certainly in the UK you know
this as I say is a pretty small country
with lots and lots to be packed into it
this would be pretty easy so again that
doesn't really stack up you know what I
mean and so there is as you just said
there is this sense of I'm not being
told the truth what are you withholding
or what are you lying about or whatever
and and yeah the it undermines trust
which you know has been a long process
so here's here's a heart right if if
there is a fiction to the narrative
right one we're being lied to
or two it's just a global history loose
nation right both of those are
inconceivable in a way right if it's
just like we think we're dying but
really we're not this isn't that this
isn't a catastrophic event it just
somehow because of the rapidity of it
because of the infectiousness of it
because of our own internal fragile
state this is kind of like waking up in
the middle of the night thinking you see
a stranger in in the corner of the room
and freaking out my body reacts as if
there's an intruder I turn on the light
oh it's not an intruder it's a pile of
laundry I didn't okay everything comes
down but if I if I can't make out the
distinction if I have to react right I'm
afraid to turn on the light I'm gonna
have to treat it like an intruder I
better get my gun you know okay
at what point just Huson nation give way
to know this isn't the case so that's
one side it's who it's a global
hallucination that we're all reacting to
in the same way and our response is
causing us to exacerbate the response
it's a it's a it's a chain reaction kind
of hallucination the other option if
it's if there isn't truly if this isn't
truly a pandemic that requires this all
the response is that governments around
the world are cooperating what wait a
minute can it possibly be the case that
China and Russia and Italy and France
and the United States and North Korea
and South Korea are cooperating to
convey a message of global pandemic and
shutting down and hiding the fact that
the hospitals are empty in order to do
what is this a one-world government like
a lot of people are saying or is this
really you know what we're at the end of
the notion of patriarchal top-down
societal structure that can operate from
rules and justice and we need to now
rely on our neighbors more than some
central authority to take care of it if
that's the case again is that a response
from the bottom up or from the top down
or is it really
kind of a an but isn't it
hallucination and as as much as it feels
like I don't like the notion of
hallucinating in some real way when I
study neuroscience and look at it that
is all I have to go on every perception
I had is my body's entire system using
my eyes and my ears and my senses and
everything telling me what am I seeing
and there are times when I see I look
outside and I see that just looks like a
calm beach and I and then when I really
understand what it is no that's a
tsunami this is a problem right and a
lot of something like the virus is
difficult for us to perceive this is an
exponential event I don't know how to
recognize an exponential event I've
heard of them I heard of Moore's law and
see what that looks like over a 50-year
period I don't know what that looks like
a three-month period yeah and this is a
big is that people don't understand the
mathematics of exponential growth and we
know this time and time again from like
those rentals of like you know we double
the population every 24 hours at what
point in the fee tree you know the
world's absolutely full on the on the
100th day when is it half full and it's
like well the mad 99th day look it's
like this is how people don't understand
and so they compared it to the flu and
they compared to all these things like
look there's less deaths yes but that's
with it running rampant that's with it
it burning out through the population
there is something when you were you
were talking of which I don't know what
this is just like my fear and my war
side coming out but there's all the
people there was someone who just did a
protest and Cooper like stop stay inside
we need to do and there was like 20
people in seth rogen he was like you're
a idiot stay stop I paid for the
tweet but like there's part of me that's
like you know what these people who want
to like be out and running their revives
give them a city give them a city don't
let them leave and let them inhabit run
wild have a hospital that's also
equipped with the doctors and nurses who
agree with that and let's see right but
like this fact that we're all dispersed
everywhere
means there's people in every city who
wants to stay who want to stay inside
for the good of health and safety of the
nurses and doctors and people who are
like this is stupid this is too far for
destroying our economy and the reason we
can't do both is because we're all inter
dispersed but if you could say okay you
want to go out and about instead of
going to jail great you're going to
Calgary Calgary is the city but cuz he
had of course up in it and it wouldn't
be Calgary be a better City than that
but like right for the next three months
you can walk about freely in this city
go ahead get crota pirates don't because
there are as a biologist there are
things about this that don't that are
weird that like the the indigenous
isolated tribes in in nor in South
America are getting this from like the
miners it looks like but their youth are
dying from it unlike the rest of us well
that's weird because if it's new to our
bodies and it's new to theirs it
shouldn't affect us differently but if
we've come and contacted with before
before and we just didn't really realize
cuz you treat it like the flu and there
was no reason to test it and we how
about like it's weird that that their
teenagers are dying and our children and
teenagers are there's some of them but
not at that same rate or is it that we
live in close proximity and we've dealt
with the flu and cold so many times and
maybe they haven't I don't know but
there's stuff here that's like yes if
we're not open about this if I can't
trust my governments and I can't trust
then I get why people are saying we
shouldn't stay inside I get our
governments I'm the first one to say our
governments are not capable of dealing
with anything complex there's still the
best we have right now and if we're
still like this in six months yeah we
need to figure it out we need to like
figure out how to rise up from within
our own apartments take back control and
that's absolutely doable just the only
thing we know is to pour out into the
streets don't do that because that's
clearly not the thing we do during
academic but it's what people know is
available I'm just gonna get more water
you know I think it's pretty hard to
separate the media clamoring for a
course of action from government policy
these days right I mean as soon as the
media does unite behind this is what we
ought to be doing governments fall into
line right because they can't they can't
stand in the face of public opinion they
don't have the capacity to do that
obviously they have to get elected so
yeah I mean I I think it's I think it's
a pretty much fundamental thing that you
can client your flag in is that you
cannot trust governments right and and
you know even if they are acting mostly
in good faith during this coronavirus
and doing what they think is best for
the population you know overall on
balance given the of the economy
and so on
you still can't trust them you still
can't trust them and you know as soon as
the emergency is over they'll they'll be
back to their old ways again so yeah I I
have a great deal of sympathy for people
who don't trust the advice of the
government just based on the fact that
you can't trust the government
so it's fair enough it's fair enough now
you're muted muted cutely thank you fix
that jury after this pandemic what we
need to be looking at is this trust and
how can we design an information census
or so that we can trust because if the
media is not it and it's the best we
have if the government's the the only
option we have yet it's not even close
to adequate to deal with these complex
issues
what can we create to do that in their
absence like I mean you saw it happening
in America Ebola okay lord president in
house had told us to stay inside but we
are gonna stay inside like a lot of me
this would be way worse if people had
listened to their president some of them
did some of them still are they're still
having some church church services and
stuff in sight in some of the places but
if they had just continued business as
usual until Trump actually caught up it
would be way worse than it actually is
and yeah anyway to redevelop a system of
trust that we can trust because we can
see transparency so you know so so it's
interesting because if I think that
you know the Charles Eisenstein piece
and his discussion recently about that
and the coming cross words is evident
like we can feel it in their bones
there's going to be a point time when we
had to change the narrative and and yet
is it y2k I know that didn't happen okay
that's weird okay this is a 2007
financial collapse right to make Clark
lapse nope that didn't happen either
okay then it's something it's it's which
one is it and then suddenly it shows up
and it's like there's something like if
we as a collective even if none of us is
individuals but the collective know
we've got to respond to this Center we
have to shift the focus so I think of it
there's a there's a model in my mind of
of a tower that's built straight up
right it it's built on conditional
architecture and it it can go very tall
but it doesn't it's very unstable from
from lateral forces right it's it's
fragile or you can build a dome right a
geodesic dome has the weight distributed
throughout it we've been operating with
the tower model right the top-down this
this fragile thing and it's to the point
now where realistically whether you're a
physicist or an economist or a
politician you can start to see this
thing is this thing is wobbly I mean it
is it wouldn't take very much to knock
it over and the only way to distribute
that is to figure out how to rely on
your neighbor more I don't know how you
make a transition it's one of the
questions that have been asking myself
is how would we make a transition from
one mode to the next I can't figure out
how to collapse a tower into that mode
but I did watch a video that was just a
quick demonstration of raising a dome
using a tower as though as that mode
right so it's in some at some point if
you've ever worked on a G it is dumb
it's kind of an interesting exercise to
do because there's one part where it's
all floppy and then you start to connect
the pieces together and all of a sudden
the rigidity of the pieces give it it
has there's a point at which when you're
putting the pieces in place it kind of
pops it sort of defies gravity because
that tends
that gives that whole structure a
cohesive
since looks magical it's not it's in the
same way it's a distributed intelligence
to the distributed structure and it
relies on each node being connected to
the nodes around it and with the right
degree of tension right so that's the
way that the cells in the body operate
and the cells in the body a body don't
listen to one CEO neuron or what
president neuron one president cell that
tells them everybody what to do
that would be failure we wouldn't be
able to respond with nearly enough
rapidity to real problems so each cell
has to be paying attention to its
neighbors and then what happens is an
emergent and emerges hallucination about
what's the best thing to do in this
moment and and it's a complex lis
adaptive emergence that happens over
time so we learn through this process
and this is kind of a shock to the
system that allows us to say okay huh
we're not really we're fragile but this
is kind of like a baby just learning how
to use limbs that are at this point just
what I don't know what what's my
intention and what is has it related to
this waiting thing in my face hmm
and I think that is that is HUGE I mean
being able to figure out how to
dismantle the tower that is there that
we know is wobbly well we build
something else or first build the thing
and then allow it and and how what does
that what does that process look like
then we have to build the scaffolding we
have to be able to build the the safety
net without relying on who clearly is
bad at the safety net just the
government and yet Who am I is very tied
and only me I mean just most people is
tied to like no weight on this thing
that's not my job that's the
government's job it's the government's
job to look after me it's the
government's job for me to get angry and
tell you how to do things even though
you'll never listen so that I eat so
that there's like this disconnect like
you are the parent I'm allowed to yell
app because you're doing it wrong as
opposed to
oh wait I'm a grown-up oh we we actually
do need to have everybody building that
geodesic dome everybody within their
capacity saying what does that look like
for you I don't get to dictate what it
looks like for anyone else but how can
we come together as sovereign
individuals and create the thing that
does connect us to our neighbor I mean
that is what I am attempting to do a
solution raising is showcase like look
we can create a potential solution
that's not divisive within an hour what
if we actually made these right there is
no left and right when it comes to are
you hungry do you want to eat there's no
left and right when it's like you need
to get from your point A to point B how
do you transport yourself there's you
know better and worse ways to do that
but those things are can be diverse
that's right we can have their versus
food system and transportation system
and not need to have one or you don't
like just one way everyone has to have
this one way we can we can create the
scaffold did you go down to sick dome I
believe so so essentially I recommend
people look to see I saw I was curious
about towers and domes you know the
construction of the dome and the way
that they demonstrated doing it has just
first build the first ring there's a
giant tower that has cables that then
you build the ring and you and you
elevate it and then you build a next
layer and you elevate it and you but
then it's a time-lapse oh you watch this
dome over time get tuned you know so
it's building the eggshell from the top
down but raising a little bit so there's
never any massive structure but after it
becomes big enough the thing that's
interesting if you look at it the dome
is actually strong enough at the point
that it's complete that it can lift the
tower the tower becomes secondary
it becomes irrelevant irrelevant to the
overall structural strength but it was
necessary in the transition so one of
the things that you mentioned Eric one
of the questions that you asked is what
is when we're cog that's one mode and
it's very automatic right it has a it's
only running because the other ones are
turning and it does it doesn't have it
doesn't have its own sense but what you
asked is what's another mode
and I think a transmission right does
that right it is a it is a movement from
one one power source to another power
source in in a in a steady kind of a way
rather than a rigid concerning
transmission right it's not all somatic
there's discernment involved it's like a
neuron right it's only when a certain
threshold is reached that the message
actually goes any further kind of thing
and so each node is filtering out the
ship before passing anything on right
whereas a cog has no choice but to pass
on all the energy that came into it
passes it on so yeah there's there's
there's agency and autonomy built in
where the cog does not have that yeah
which is which is the notion that I
think I want to give gym rats we all
have to be on the same side or when Doug
rushkoff talks about being on Team human
if team human means that we all have to
agree to the same on the top side to
define our actions it's not nuanced
enough it doesn't have enough of the of
that capacity for each of the nodes to
know okay what's my what's my action
here and that this question is a
beautiful question Who am I yeah and it
is it's about helping people find out
which cog they are I think on some bad
connotation I like to think of it as a
puzzle piece which is a whole different
connotation for autistic people which I
don't care about but uh I mean whatever
that like we're all walking around with
our own individual puzzle piece not even
realizing it's like well we're trying to
be the whole picture but we can't be all
you can be is your puzzle piece and who
do you fit with so you can make the
bigger picture and how do we coordinate
with that because no one person can do
it all no one person can hold all of the
information which is where a lot of my
ideas have come from is like I want
access to all of human knowledge which I
can never get in my brain because nobody
can so how can we get it in an outside
thing that I can have access to and then
in order to put that out in the world
access to it I have figured all the
other pieces that we need that are
nothing to do with necessarily knowledge
that are had we feed ourselves how to
clothe ourselves how do we and we govern
how do we have that thing where this
it's the cell next to you I mean I was
just gardening because I'm trying to put
in a garden even though I know I'm not
I'm not great at it I never seem to
manage to make things grow but I'm
trying to dig up the roots of like the
blackberry bushes that are really
prickly because I know how blackberry
bushes are not prickly and I'm trying to
get to grow there and the root structure
of like you it's really such a like pull
one root in is one Johnny but easier
verses of course you can't pull the
whole thing up but you can pull each
individual root and then and then pull
it up and no one told those roots to
grow the roots are all intermixed with
the other ones they're all looking after
their own self-interests really right
there try to get their most nutrients
they're trying to propagate but in so
doing they've made the the root
structure more stable right not for me
I want the roots not to be there but
like for them there's something very
stable about that if we follow what
nature does we can get to a system that
isn't top-down it isn't
doesn't matter how much I yell at that
root not to grow there it's gonna grow
that doesn't care what I wanted to do
but it in so doing is looking at its own
self-interest and it's part of the
ecosystem and making something better
right it is stabilizing the soil so that
other things can use that stable soil to
grow as well it's not simply choking out
but it's pretty much to be honest do
pretty much choke out once they get
established nothing else grows they're
they're they're little they are
there are worthy adversary though I tell
you you've got to respect I mean much as
I hate them you have to respect them
they are well adapted south and they're
vicious yet strangely the blackberry
bush isn't as hard to pull up the roots
as the whatever other horrible flower
thing that was out in my yard that was
much harder to define those roots and
take them up the blackberry one actually
isn't that held in there like it's very
different gate everywhere yeah I had a
whole field full of them I streamed them
down
first of all and then as they started
growing back again started digging them
out one by one
and I'm convinced this one giant plant
covering like a 500 square meter field
it's one giant they are all connected to
each other in it and in it you've met
and I mean some of the roots Susie some
of them are like this thick and they are
meters and meters meters and meters long
6 7 8 10 12 meters long and some of the
Liana's they grow up and over the oak
trees the oak trees are 12 15 meters
high and they're brambles go up over and
down again we can figure out how to be
brambles we got it
like if we can figure out how in any
root is left behind we can regrow the
species right where it's like even if
it's just one root it has the
information it needs to start regrowing
to start where it's not it's not
required to have this central body you
know if we kill the central body oh
these things are still coming back
unless you get every last one of them
and if we can create in that way that
hopefully isn't like a weed it's taking
everything over it's a welcome portion
but what's interesting isn't it when we
get clever enough that we can
essentially expand without limits right
then we need to become our own limiting
factor somehow or other you know
otherwise the general may know somehow
or other we need to install our own
limiting factors that's mm-hmm that's
something that we have difficulty with
right now right so it's actually one of
the I'm not gonna be able to remember
his name right now Russell has mine his
first or last name is Russell Brad do it
Russell way now it's Stuart Russell I
believe is is his name or Russell Stuart
it's one of the two
he wrote a he wrote a book called human
compatible which is about artificial
intelligence he's the first the way that
it's build is that he's the first true a
I researcher deep a and deeply
knowledgeable about AI is talking about
the risk and potential of artificial
intelligence and what do we actually
need to be aware of what are the actual
risks how do we how do we
move forward with the center which is
gonna make sense and one of the things
that he says what's human compatible is
the notion that we have to make sure
that it cares what we think about what
it's doing you know which is a notion
that's similar to what as a chasm offset
in the three rules of robotics but it's
actually okay that's oversimplified how
do you actually do that so that you
don't say hey AI robot go and do this
for me you say here's what I'm looking
for what you know as I'm going is there
a feedback mechanism that you
continually check and say isn't moving
in the direction that you expect or is
it now wait a minute no that's
unintended I didn't expect that to
happen hold on pause let's wait a minute
so it's interesting to think about that
is it's like okay yeah if you could
actually do that it's complicated it's
not a simple task but if you could do
that maybe that's okay and then I pause
in that backup and I think let's
actually give a voice to every species
on a planet and have a vote who thinks
that humans ought to be able to develop
artificial intelligence that has human
interest as its core motivation I would
say you get a veto human motivation like
don't be on our side the dogs but yeah
no absolutely so we're getting to the
hour and I have to go to get to the next
thing does anyone have any closing
statements and then if you guys want to
hang out or we say goodbye to YouTube
that's something else to mention that
wasn't it Samira cozy David all right
Erik anything yeah just just just coming
back to the original Who am I question
this lockdown is an excellent
opportunity for people to actually do a
little bit of exploration into this
right mm-hmm you know ask themselves
serious questions about you know is you
know if my job has been deemed
non-essential is it actually
non-essential I mean you know could the
world live without the job that I'm
doing you know these
and and as David mentioned before I
think it was Nora said that wasn't it
like who am i if I don't have my job and
I don't have my career and I don't have
any money and it whatever you know who
am I after that you know the yeah using
this time to try and try to think about
maybe answering that question would be
closing statement right goodbye YouTube
thank you see you next week for what who
are people oh you're like this